what do you imagine?
ماذا ستتخيلون؟
Most people think about either empty space
يعتقدُ معظم الناس إما مساحة فارغة
or clear blue sky
أو سماء زرقاء صافية
or sometimes trees dancing in the wind.
أو في بعض الأحيان، أشجار ترقص مع الريح.
And then I remember my high school chemistry teacher with really long socks
وأتذكر أستاذي للكيمياء في المدرسة الثانوية وهو مرتديًا الجوارب الطويلة
at the blackboard,
عند السبورة
drawing diagrams of bubbles connected to other bubbles,
يرسمُ رسومًا بيانية لـفقاعات متصلة بفقاعات أخرى
and describing how they vibrate and collide in a kind of frantic soup.
ويصف كيف تهتز وتصطدم في نوع من الحساء المغلي.
But really, we tend not to think about the air that much at all.
في الواقع، نحن لا نميل لتخيل الهواء كذلك إطلاقًا.
We notice it mostly
نحنُ نلاحظه في الغالب
when there's some kind of unpleasant sensory intrusion upon it,
عندما يوجد هناك نوع من التداخل الحسي المزعج عليه،
like a terrible smell or something visible like smoke or mist.
مثل رائحة فظيعة أو شيء مرئي مثل الدخان أو الضباب.
But it's always there.
ولكنه لا يزال هنا.
It's touching all of us right now.
إنه يلمسُ كل واحد منا الآن،
It's even inside us.
حتى إنه في داخلنا.
Our air is immediate, vital and intimate.
هواؤنا فوريّ وحيويّ وقريب منّا.
And yet, it's so easily forgotten.
ومع ذلك، فنحن ننساه بسهولة.
So what is the air?
إذا ما هو الهواء؟
It's the combination of the invisible gases that envelop the Earth,
هو مزيج من الغازات غير المرئية التي تغلّف الأرض،
attracted by the Earth's gravitational pull.
ويتمُ جذبها بواسطة تأثير الجاذبية الأرضية.
And even though I'm a visual artist,
وعلى الرغم من أنني فنانة تشكيلية،
I'm interested in the invisibility of the air.
إلأ أنني مهتمة بخفاء الهواء.
I'm interested in how we imagine it,
أنا مهتمة بكيفية تخيّله،
how we experience it
كيف نختبره
and how we all have an innate understanding of its materiality
وكيف أننا جميعاً لدينا بالفطرة فهم لأهميته بالنسبة لنا
through breathing.
من خلال التنفس.
All life on Earth changes the air through gas exchange,
جميع أشكال الحياة على الأرض تغيّر الهواء من خلال تبادل الغازات،
and we're all doing it right now.
وجميعنا نفعل ذلك الآن.
Actually, why don't we all right now together take
في الواقع، لماذا لا نأخذ معًا الآن
one big, collective, deep breath in.
نفساً عميقاً جماعياً.
Ready? In. (Inhales)
مستعدون؟ للداخل. (شهيق)
And out. (Exhales)
ثم للخارج. (زفير)
That air that you just exhaled,
هذا الهواء الذي قمت بإخراجه الآن،
you enriched a hundred times in carbon dioxide.
لقد قمت بزيادة ثاني أكسيد الكربون مائة مرة.
So roughly five liters of air per breath, 17 breaths per minute
إذن حوالي خمسة لترات من الهواء بالتنفس، 17 نفساً في الدقيقة
of the 525,600 minutes per year,
لـ 525,600 دقيقة سنوياً،
comes to approximately 45 million liters of air,
ما يقرب من 45 مليون لتر من الهواء،
enriched 100 times in carbon dioxide,
زودت ثاني أكسيد الكربون مائة مرة.
just for you.
فقط بالنسبة لك أنت.
Now, that's equivalent to about 18 Olympic-sized swimming pools.
الآن، يعادل هذا حوالي 18 حمام سباحة أوليمبي.
For me, air is plural.
بالنسبة لي، الهواء هو مجموع عدة مكونات.
It's simultaneously as small as our breathing
في نفس الوقت هو في صغره يشبه تنفسنا
and as big as the planet.
وفي كبره يعادل الكوكب.
And it's kind of hard to picture.
ونوعه يعدّ من الصعب تصوره.
Maybe it's impossible, and maybe it doesn't matter.
ربما هو مستحيل، وربما لا يهم على الإطلاق.
Through my visual arts practice,
من خلال ممارستي للفنون البصرية،
I try to make air, not so much picture it,
أحاول خلق الهواء، ليس فقط تخيّله،
but to make it visceral and tactile and haptic.
أحاول جعله محسوسًا وملموسًا.
I try to expand this notion of the aesthetic, how things look,
أحاول توسيع الفكر الجمالي، عن كيف تبدو الأشياء،
so that it can include things like how it feels on your skin
لكي يتضمن أشياء مثل كيف تشعر بالهواء على بشرتك
and in your lungs,
وداخل رئتيك،
and how your voice sounds as it passes through it.
وكيف يبدو صوتك عندما يمر خلاله.
I explore the weight, density and smell, but most importantly,
أنا أفحص الوزن، والكثافة والرائحة، لكن الأكثر أهمية،
I think a lot about the stories we attach to different kinds of air.
أنا أفكر كثيرًا في القصص التي تتعلق بأنواع مختلفة من الهواء.
This is a work I made in 2014.
هذا عمل قمت به عام 2014.
It's called "Different Kinds of Air: A Plant's Diary,"
يطلق عليه "أنواع مختلفة من الهواء: يوميات النبات،"
where I was recreating the air from different eras in Earth's evolution,
حيث كنت أقوم بإعادة تخليق الهواء من مختلف العصور في رحلة تطور الأرض،
and inviting the audience to come in and breathe them with me.
وأدعو الحضورلأن يأتوا ويستنشقوا هذا الهواء معي.
And it's really surprising, so drastically different.
وهو حقًا وبشكل مفاجئ مختلف جذريًا.
Now, I'm not a scientist,
الآن، أنا لست عالمة،
but atmospheric scientists will look for traces
ولكن علماء الغلاف الجوي سوف يبحثون عن آثار
in the air chemistry in geology,
في كيمياء الهواء في الجيولوجيا،
a bit like how rocks can oxidize,
مثل كيف يمكن للصخور أن تتأكسد،
and they'll extrapolate that information and aggregate it,
وسيستنتجون هذه المعلومات ويُجمعونها،
such that they can pretty much form a recipe
وبهذه الطريقة يمكنهم تقريبًا تكوين وصفة
for the air at different times.
للهواء من مختلف العصور.
Then I come in as the artist and take that recipe
ثم أدخل أنا كالفنانة وآخذ هذه الوصفة
and recreate it using the component gases.
وأُعيد تخليقها باستخدام الغازات المكونة.
I was particularly interested in moments of time
لقد كنت مهتمةً خصيصًا في بعض الوقت
that are examples of life changing the air,
بأشكال الحياة التي تغير الهواء،
but also the air that can influence how life will evolve,
ولكن أيضًا بالهواء القادرعلى التأثير علي تطور الحياة،
like Carboniferous air.
مثل هواء العصر الفحمي.
It's from about 300 to 350 million years ago.
الذي كان بين 300 إلي 350 مليون سنة مضت.
It's an era known as the time of the giants.
هو عصر معروف بعصر العمالقة.
So for the first time in the history of life,
لأول مرة في تاريخ البشرية،
lignin evolves.
يتطور اللجنين.
That's the hard stuff that trees are made of.
هو المادة الخام الصلبة التي تتكون منها الأشجار.
So trees effectively invent their own trunks at this time,
وبالتالي فالأشجار كانت تكون جذوعها الخاصة بفاعلية في ذلك الزمن،
and they get really big, bigger and bigger,
وتزداد ضخامةً أكثر فأكثر،
and pepper the Earth,
وتملؤ الأرض،
releasing oxygen, releasing oxygen, releasing oxygen,
وتخرج أكسجين، وتخرج أكسجين، وتخرج أكسجين،
such that the oxygen levels are about twice as high
وبهذا كانت معدلات الأكسجين تقريبًا ضعف
as what they are today.
ما هي عليه اليوم.
And this rich air supports massive insects --
وهذا الهواء الغني بالأكسجين يدعم حشرات هائلة --
huge spiders and dragonflies with a wingspan of about 65 centimeters.
عنكبوتات ويعاسيب ضخمة لها باع جناح يصل إلي 65 سنتيمتر.
To breathe, this air is really clean and really fresh.
للتنفس، هذا الهواء حقًا نظيف ونقي.
It doesn't so much have a flavor,
ليس له طعم واضح،
but it does give your body a really subtle kind of boost of energy.
ولكنه يمدّ جسمك بدفعة خفيّة من الطاقة.
It's really good for hangovers.
جيد جدًا للدوار الناتج عن شرب الخمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or there's the air of the Great Dying --
أو نتحدث عن هواء عصر الموت العظيم --
that's about 252.5 million years ago,
والذي كان منذ 252.5 مليون سنة مضت،
just before the dinosaurs evolve.
قبل تطوّر الديناصورات مباشرةً.
It's a really short time period, geologically speaking,
هي فترة زمنية ضئيلة للغاية، من ناحية جيولوجية،
from about 20- to 200,000 years.
تمتد لحوالي 20 إلي 200,000 سنة.
Really quick.
سريعة للغاية.
This is the greatest extinction event in Earth's history,
إنه عصر الانقراض الأكبر في تاريخ البشرية،
even bigger than when the dinosaurs died out.
أكبر حتي من فترة انقراض الديناصورات.
Eighty-five to 95 percent of species at this time die out,
انقرضت 85 إلي 95 بالمائة من فصائل هذا العصر،
and simultaneous to that is a huge, dramatic spike in carbon dioxide,
وبالتزامن كان هناك تصاعد ضخم ودراماتيكي في معدلات ثاني أكسيد الكربون،
that a lot of scientists agree
وهو ما اتفق عليه الكثيرمن العلماء
comes from a simultaneous eruption of volcanoes
أتي نتيجة ثورة البراكين في ذلك الوقت
and a runaway greenhouse effect.
والاحتباس الحراري الجامح.
Oxygen levels at this time go to below half of what they are today,
كانت معدلات الأكسجين في ذلك الوقت أقل من نصف ما هي عليه الآن،
so about 10 percent.
حوالي 10 بالمائة.
So this air would definitely not support human life,
لذا لم يكن الهواء ليدعم حياة الإنسان،
but it's OK to just have a breath.
ولكن لا بأس أن تأخذ نفسًا فقط.
And to breathe, it's oddly comforting.
التتنفس، هو شعور مريح بشكل غريب.
It's really calming, it's quite warm
مهدئ بحق، ودافئ إلى حد كبير
and it has a flavor a little bit like soda water.
و له مذاق يشبه إلى حد ما المياه الغازية.
It has that kind of spritz, quite pleasant.
يشبه السبريتز(شراب كحولي)، مبهج إلى حد كبير.
So with all this thinking about air of the past,
لذا مع كل هذا التفكير في هواء الماضي،
it's quite natural to start thinking about the air of the future.
من الطبيعي أن نبدأ بالتفكير في هواء المستقبل.
And instead of being speculative with air
وبدلًا من المضاربة مع الهواء
and just making up what I think might be the future air,
وفقط تصنيع ما أعتقد سيكون عليه حال الهواء في المستقبل،
I discovered this human-synthesized air.
قمت باكتشاف هذا الهواء البشري المُصنّع.
That means that it doesn't occur anywhere in nature,
ما يعني أنه لا يتواجد بأي مكان في الطبيعة،
but it's made by humans in a laboratory
لكنه صنع بواسطة بعض الناس في أحد المعامل
for application in different industrial settings.
للتطبيق في إعدادات صناعية مختلفة.
Why is it future air?
لماذا هو هواء المستقبل؟
Well, this air is a really stable molecule
حسنًا، هذا الهواء عبارة عن مركب مستقر جدًا
that will literally be part of the air once it's released,
و الذي حرفيًا سيكون جزء من الهواء بمجرد تحريره،
for the next 300 to 400 years, before it's broken down.
لمدة 300 إلي 400 سنة قادمة قبل أن يتعطّل.
So that's about 12 to 16 generations.
ما يعني حوالي 12 إلي 16 جيل.
And this future air has some very sensual qualities.
وهواء المستقبل هذا له بعض الصفات الحسّية جدًا.
It's very heavy.
هو ثقيل للغاية.
It's about eight times heavier than the air we're used to breathing.
أثقل بثمان مرات من الهواء الذي اعتدنا على تنفسه.
It's so heavy, in fact, that when you breathe it in,
هو ثقيل للغاية حقيقةً لدرجة أنه عندما تستنشقه،
whatever words you speak are kind of literally heavy as well,
مهما تكن الكلمات التي تطلقها، تكن حرفيًا نوعًا ما ثقيلة أيضًا،
so they dribble down your chin and drop to the floor
تتدحرج إلى أسفل ذقنك وتسقط على الأرض
and soak into the cracks.
وتنقع في الشقوق.
It's an air that operates quite a lot like a liquid.
هو هواء يعمل إلى حد كبير كسائل.
Now, this air comes with an ethical dimension as well.
الآن يأتي هذا الهواء ببعد أخلاقي أيضًا.
Humans made this air,
البشر صنعوا هذا الهواء،
but it's also the most potent greenhouse gas
لكنه أيضًا أقوى الغازات الدفيئة
that has ever been tested.
التي سبق اختبارها.
Its warming potential is 24,000 times that of carbon dioxide,
قدرته علي إحداث الإحترار تمثّل 24,000 مرة قدرة ثاني أكسيد الكربون،
and it has that longevity of 12 to 16 generations.
وله عمر يمتدّ من 12 إلي 16 جيل.
So this ethical confrontation is really central to my work.
هذه المواجهة الأخلاقية مركزية في عملي.
(In a lowered voice) It has another quite surprising quality.
(في صوت منخفض) يمتلك خاصية أخرى مفاجئة إلى حد كبير.
It changes the sound of your voice quite dramatically.
يغير هذا الهواء صوتك بشكل دراماتيكي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So when we start to think -- ooh! It's still there a bit.
عنما نبدأ بالتفكير -- أوه! لا يزال هناك بعض منه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When we think about climate change,
عندما نفكّر في التغيّر المناخي،
we probably don't think about giant insects and erupting volcanoes
ربما لا نفكر في حشرات عملاقة وبراكين ثائرة
or funny voices.
أو أصوات مضحكة.
The images that more readily come to mind
الصور التي تأتي سريعًا إلى العقل
are things like retreating glaciers and polar bears adrift on icebergs.
هي تلك الأشياء مثل تراجع الأنهار الجليدية والدببة القطبية علي جرف الجبال الجليدية.
We think about pie charts and column graphs
نفكّر في المخططات الدائرية والرسومات البيانية العمودية
and endless politicians talking to scientists wearing cardigans.
والنقاشات الغير منتهية بين السياسيين والعلماء المرتديين للجارديغانز.
But perhaps it's time we start thinking about climate change
لكن ربما هذا هو الوقت لكي نبدأ بالتفكير في التغيّر المناخي
on the same visceral level that we experience the air.
علي نفس المستوى المتوغل الذي اختبرنا فيه الهواء.
Like air, climate change is simultaneously at the scale of the molecule,
مثل الهواء، التغير المناخي متزامن مع مقياس المركّب،
the breath and the planet.
النفس والكوكب.
It's immediate, vital and intimate,
مباشرةً يكون حيويًا وعاطفيًا،
as well as being amorphous and cumbersome.
بالإضافة إلى كونه عديم الشكل وثقيلًا.
And yet, it's so easily forgotten.
ومع ذلك، من السهل جدًا نسيانه.
Climate change is the collective self-portrait of humanity.
التغيّر المناخي هو الصورة الذاتية المُجمّعة للإنسانية.
It reflects our decisions as individuals,
تعكس قراراتنا كأشخاص،
as governments and as industries.
كحكومات وكصناعات.
And if there's anything I've learned from looking at air,
وإذا كان هناك شيئ تعلمته من النظر إلى الهواء،
it's that even though it's changing, it persists.
هو أنّه علي الرغم من أنّه يتغيّر إلا أنه ما زال مثابرًا.
It may not support the kind of life that we'd recognize,
قد لا يدعم هذا نوع الحياة التي سنواجهها،
but it will support something.
ولكنّه سيدعم شيئَا ما.
And if we humans are such a vital part of that change,
وإذا كنّا نحن البشر جزءًا حيويًا من هذا التغيّر،
I think it's important that we can feel the discussion.
أعتقد أنه من المهم أن نتمكن من الإحساس بهذا النقاش.
Because even though it's invisible,
لأنه على الرغم من كونه غير مرئي،
humans are leaving a very vibrant trace in the air.
إلّا أنّ البشر يتركون أثرًا نابضًا للغاية في الهواء.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)